and welcome to another awakening from
the meaning crisis discord QA our guest
today is a guy Sen stock who is not
going to be unknown to many people here
he is the founder and creator of the
circling method and the circling
Institute
he's been facilitating transformation
for individuals groups and corporations
for more than 20 years is a BFA from the
San Francisco Art Institute and is the
co-founder of the event center for
excellence and the Bay Area men's circle
he's an artist philosopher poet body
worker and visionary thank you so much
for being here guy thank you
so I'd like to usually I start off by
asking some introductory questions so so
you are known as the creator of circling
so like that ask you two questions about
this and you can decide the order you
want it you want to answer them in okay
like unit I'd like you to tell us what
circling is but also what's the story of
circling how did you what led you to
come up with it
what was the journey that brought you
there yeah well if I can ask you just so
I can kind of tune into the listening a
little bit more like if I were to ask
you the same question what circling is
based on what you do know or don't know
what what would you say sure for my
understanding it's sort of a I think of
it as a meditative discussion where the
parties are trying to communicate with
each other to really to really see into
one another's to really put themselves
and the others shoes to understand not
just what they're saying but what
they're feeling in the moment you know
in the moment that they're talking yeah
totally and what and why would you do
such a thing if you wouldn't well for me
from what I've heard and we so we've
been introduced to the concept so this
is the awakening for the meeting crisis
discord which is based on John for
Vicki's work and so a lot of us here
have discovered circling through through
drawn and from what I understand
and I'm eager to experience that
circling can be can be transformative my
my inkling from from trying it a few
times with some some demos and and
hearing about it is that it will help
put you in tune with other people in a
way that you may not have been before
that you'll start to see things and
other people you know seeing their being
mode see see see them for who they are
in a way seeing things about them
characteristics about them the more Ness
of them so to speak that you may not
have noticed before and and then so
interact with them in a way that you may
not have been able to before without the
practice yeah that sounds good to me
you keyed in on the the quality of
circling I think you know it's funny I
my my answer that question has been
evolving and I think it'll just
continued to evolve because it's a
circling circling for me in the
development of the circling method right
has been something that I felt like we
discovered but it wasn't like we were
looking for something we discovered it
as an experience together me and a group
of friends back I think it was like late
90s 1998 I think it was um and just
spontaneously started having experiences
together that were just profound which
met like and I've been I have been since
then been been asking myself the same
question that Jerry the guy who I
started it with like asked me after was
all done our first our first experience
and we got done in our like it was like
twelve hours later we had had this like
experience of what we now call circling
happened and and he was he he looked
back to where we were and he pointed in
that direction he and he didn't have a
word for it I was like yeah and I
pointed back at the same direction and I
didn't have a word for it and it was
this really beautiful kind of
tongue-tied
moment but we both knew exactly that we
had just experienced something that was
stood out as distinct from all the other
profound experiencing things that we've
been we were having at that time and
then we just spontaneously put our hands
out and just shook and committed to
whatever that was and I and I would say
that I have been continually finding out
what that is and and then shaped by what
that is in the finding it out and I
think that's just that process of of
leaning into some sense of
intelligibility that's beyond me yet
draws me and then in order to understand
it to bring words to it I on some level
in order to conform to it it ends up
transforming me that's been my
relationship with circling and it's
still it's still going on right it's a
little happening right now as we're
talking because people ask me questions
about it there's still a sense of like I
I often to myself anyways think about
surfing
I imagine circling as a as an entity
sometimes of like and there's a sense in
which she's still she's still revealing
herself to be and when she does my life
I look different my life looks different
how everything shows up for me looks
different so how would you describe that
transformative effect that that people
that you experience and that you you've
seen other people experience well
there's a lot of different components to
it
right but you know I I think on some
level it's interesting because when we
when we started this right would when
circlings just started there was a way
where our vocabulary wasn't we didn't
have the vocabulary to basically
describe what we were talking about
right because I think that authenticity
is really in a lot of the a lot of the
ways of describing this kind of thing
have to do with like a normal notion of
self right of of in some sense
a sense of self fulfillment or
self-reflection and reflected upon self
right that I somehow own right but I
think I think what circling really gets
at to gets at is a deeper level of
authenticity which is how we in so many
ways from the very beginning right like
the very beginning when we're like
infants right we're born into a world
and how I become is through the
attention and and my family and contact
and a tournament with other people how I
know that I am how I am shaped how I I'm
just close to myself is can is so deeply
entwined with my environment with you
know and all the stuff all the research
that they're doing on attachment theory
is like you know really recognizing this
of like there's a certain amount of
distance from the mother's face that if
then the infant doesn't have it gets
there's all kinds of symptoms so I think
it's like if we just look at
relationship being being ourselves in
relationship they're almost
indistinguishable from each other and I
would say that like that's pretty well
known in like psychology right for the
most part but I don't think we have much
of a way of knowing how that continues
through our own our whole lives right
that we're constantly coming into being
through our relationships and so
circling you could say is the
transformation has to do with what's
just so native soil to being a self on
some level right which is is coming into
into conversations and having
relationships that are mutually
self-disclosing right in a way that that
inspires us and calls us beyond
ourselves
that's what's possible in interactions
now I think that I think that the the
fact that there's something called
circling right announces that that's not
how relationships usually go right like
right like they don't usually go that
way
but they could and so circling is all
about like if there were postures that
you sit in if there
if there were muscles that you exercise
if there was a an underlying logos right
that gave rise to allowing relationships
to open in that way together circling is
like extracted that out and made it a
yoga so so you on your website you
describe yourself as someone who pays
attention in such a way that will allow
the parties Lao you see you allow allow
you and I to see and hear those things
which have always been present yet never
occurred to you is this a skill that do
you think this is a skill you've always
had that that's innate it you were just
born with or is this something that can
be cultivated in people what do you
think what do you think what do you
think what do you think it what are you
kind of getting from what I'm saying so
far my my guess is that I think that
well certain people probably are are
more naturally tuned into other people
as well but I think that it is something
that everyone can work on and get better
at and through practices like like
circling right totally yeah absolutely I
think it's like I mean I think
personally I probably have a particular
acuity for this this is why it spoke to
me so much however I have to say at
least from my own experience I'm so much
better at it than I was when we first
started right so it has me think that it
is and also from what I've just seen
from teaching people for the last 20
years in in becoming good circulars
right is it is interesting because your
question kind of like points to
something that's I think really quite
deep right where it's always a paradox
and teaching this right because there
are skills and there are ways of saying
things there's
things to pay attention to there's
certain kind of like you could say best
practices for ways of communicating and
attitudes and all that kind of stuff
right but when it comes down to it I
don't think a relationship is a skill I
don't think I think it's a capacity
right it's a capacity to be related so
it's in fact it's strange when somebody
has a bunch of those skills but they
don't have any capacity to be in a
relationship and they're and they use
all the communication techniques and
stuff like that it ends up just feeling
really wonky so I think it's like that
starts to speak to where I think
circling and learning how to circle and
what it starts to get at when people
talk about being transformed right I
think the transformation that they're
probably speaking of is that there's
that circle and kind of in a certain
sense demands right calls forth aspire
to you aspiring to coming into full
contact with another person right
deepening your capacity to be related
and that's really a being mode I think
is is from would point out right it's
not a having mode so it's really tricky
there's like this is where it's kind of
most people that if you've ever
experienced circling it's like filled
with these weird paradoxes right it's
like it's almost like when you go to a
circling thing and you hear people
describe it you think you're talking
about like you're talking about
mysticism or something and in it and it
is in that way right because it's like
right on this mode of like where I can
become a better communicator right
however in becoming a better
communicator right I must be able to
deepen my capacity to communicate right
and and I think that that's where you
start to look at like development right
you start to use terms like
transformation development right the
becoming someone who could be good at
that so it's so I think that's where
when people talk about like deep
transformative experiences I think it's
it starts that's that you start to I
think that's one way of starting to get
at it
does that make sense yeah that's accent
excellent one way that you put it on
your website that was intriguing to me
is you said I can I can I'm someone who
can sit next to a stranger and have a
conversation with them such that the
stranger walks away living inside a
completely different world yeah yeah
yeah you know and I think like what I've
been thinking about at like recently is
I think one of the things that circling
really really really does a virtue that
it that that underline circling and and
and is a practice of is reverence right
because they I think it's and just like
with the virtue like the way Socrates
simple taunt like the Platon is talked
about a virtue it's like a virtue is
like a one-level it's like something
that's already and Nate Lee there but
it's also something that you can strive
towards and when I think what's when it
comes down to it I think what everything
falls right those kinds of deep
connections with people falls on your
ability to to find yourself in a
reverence of with a another person and
to cultivate that sense of reverence and
I think that like when it comes down to
it it's the reverence that I experienced
and have cultivated through practicing
it that naturally flows into like oh you
know someone kind of listening to me or
somebody who's circling and go oh
they're a really good listener like yes
we're a really good listener but I think
all of that is expressions of the
ability to continually be in like have
the capacity to be in reverence and I
think that's really when it comes down
to it as an exercise if it was circling
was cultivating something I think it's
cultivating that at the deepest level
and so like a lot of time people end up
with this experience of what like
reverence leads to which are these
experiences of awe because reverence is
predicated on a anza on this awareness
of my own limitations and
that there's something beyond me that is
is something that I could I could never
fully understand right that's that that
attunement to reality in such a way and
attuning to people in that way of that
deep respect and reverence I think is
what is the it's a the machinery of that
I think is what what circling really
does cultivate in a big way
that's excellent so I'd like to open up
this to two questions if you could for
the audio and say say your name at the
beginning the question it can be your
your your your discord name doesn't have
to be a real name who has a question
fooor guy don't be shy I will I'll throw
out a question I could yeah go ahead
Mike great um hello guy thanks for
coming here and doing this you're back
nice to meet you Mike nice to meet you
so I'm curious I really enjoyed a lot of
the conversations that I've seen you
give and I'm definitely enjoying this
offer that you're providing for us here
now and I'm just curious admittedly
feeling as though to struggle to get the
question out sorry I think we lost you
for a bit there Mike you just start out
a start over so so sorry can you hear me
now if I've been noting my my sound has
been cutting in and out so it might be
Mike yeah you're you're cutting out
again yeah you're cutting in and out
oops I'm gonna pass because I'm how all
right you know what if you'd like you
could type it into the the event
listening party text and
I'll read it out okay sure I'll do that
great who else has a question or a
question or I just love to get to know
you guys and just hear what you're
hearing and what's on your mind
sure hey I'm mercury um
mercury I actually sent you a message
I'd love to have you for a podcast on my
channel but for now I'll start with so
this circling practice and the changes
you find it makes in yourself and you
have any for how that's going to ripple
out into society at this time and to
maybe tie it into the way the pandemic
currently has created a unique
opportunity for restructuring and how do
you see your expertise working into how
we might move in a better direction as
we begin to reactivate Society oh I mean
that's a really good question well first
of all so what when I think about when I
think about myself
and my understanding of legs like things
like society and culture and the world I
personally feel I feel like in some
level like I'm I'm kind of an ant on top
of a writing on an elephant's back that
can oh and I can only see an inch in
front of me right so there's a I I just
wanted just presents like where I come
from what that is like first of all I
actually don't even know what's going on
and I I stay I feel very humbled by all
the changes so I'm I I don't know I
don't know exactly what's going on and
what society needs or even what society
is however that being said right I think
that there's one of the
big big dilemmas it seems that were
inside of right is actually Chris and
Chris and John talked about this in the
paper that they wrote I thought it was
brilliant with the way that they put it
we're like we're in some kind of weird
spot where we only recognize right we've
we've only recognized like first person
present and third position right and
we've lost the sense of the other right
in in in precisely in other words like
awe and you can see it at all of like
the kind of you know the the identity
politics and you know all all that stuff
right where people are becoming more and
more identified with a label or their
group or their gender or whatever it is
right and we've lost contact with the
sensibility that one becomes who one is
in and through dialogue and through
relationship right the transformative
power of that right and if you lose that
that that spoken the wheel all you're
left with is kind of worrying games
right and all the things that come along
with this so I think it's like circling
happens to just really speak to a way of
restoring the recognition of the other
at a very simple level right to really
kind of look at somebody and and and
begin to see like see them as distinct
from your view of them and and begin to
open up and begin to listen to them
beyond what you could already think by
yourself
I think that's of that I think that's an
ancient value I think that goes way back
and I think it's it is strikingly gone
right now like in the in the normal
discourse like that like the
governmental discourse and it's like
it's really scary on that in that
respect I also think it has something to
do with like being in it in the age of
technology from the Heidegger sense of
the word right that I do also think that
we
we are in a time that we particularly
don't understand right which is what is
you know if we if we look at if we look
at how technology has has mitigated so
much of our communication and I I think
it's a profound change that that I think
we're gonna look back on and go wow this
was like the this was like a huge thing
that just happened right where where we
started to separate when I need to
relate to you I can actually like I can
text you I can email you I can do all
these things to relay information to you
without having to go through the awkward
experience that it is of being with
another person in communication and
tolerating that ambiguity there's so
many different ways that we don't have
to do that anymore
and it's in its and of course like all
other technologies like all of their
innovations like it will allow us it'll
it will just we will naturally move
towards what's easiest right and not
towards what's hard and I think that
when we've like with the answering
machine where I think was the first way
I think where is it first started right
was where was where I can like when I
have a communication for you I can
actually don't have to go through the
the conversational you know relating
that happens and that level of
conversing on a is how we become who we
are so I think there's also another part
of it which is what why something like
circling even makes sense right in this
time speaks to the time because on one
level I think circling the vet there is
such a thing as like a yoga for inner
like intersubjectivity is such a strange
thing right in but it but it makes sense
that if we've eliminated so much of that
right in our culture to come and hit
like to come and have to do like a yoga
right and concentrate just like a gym is
for our bodies like going in in in doing
exercises of relating
is something that's only emerged in the
last 20 20 years but I think it speaks
to that so I think it's like I think
circling as a practice points to
developing capacities that are probably
central to what's gonna have us move
forward excellent
mike has posted his question I'm
struggling to ask I'm struggling to ask
the question because I feel it's a bit
of a weighted question but I'm curious
if you consider circling a form of
spiritual practice and if so or if not
why and thank you for your response
let's see we just think about that for a
second well I think there's a cop
there's a couple things like so for me
it's been a spiritual practice through
the experience of it I think as a
practice though that it hasn't been
explicitly explicitly spiritual I think
it's been very very useful for it right
because there's a there's a way because
it's like it's a it's a practice right
there's there's not there's there's not
stuff that you have to believe about it
right so it's not propositional in that
way however it seems to afford a kind of
spirituality or are waking up to a
spirituality through people's experience
and and in some ways you know as John's
pointed out one of these he noticed is
that you know he goes to a circling
group and everyone's Deena using this
kind of mystical spiritual language
right and I I think that points to what
it affords but I think part of why it
affords that is because it doesn't it
doesn't presuppose spirituality so yeah
everyone that I you know everyone who
gets really involved in circling all of
them basically I think what most of them
would probably say if he asked him like
is this a spiritual practice I think
that for them
they said yes it would would be it
definitely engages the machinery right
to use John's language that's that is
the very much the same machinery that
that makes room for spiritual
experiences and its feelings of
connectedness and all of that stuff
likes cognitively emotionally and BA in
Anna bodied way so I hope that answer is
did that answer your question very much
I'm hoping you might be able to hear me
and I don't cut out yeah yeah do you
feel as though I thought you gave a
really wonderful example in sort of
pointing out it very much how I'm
feeling with regard to or like how how
do we on the one hand it sounds to me as
though you're expressing yes or you did
I heard affirmation on part of
expression yes there there is for
yourself
it's a spiritual practice that's going
along but at the same time on what seems
is though a very social level in in
light of kind of the much larger worldly
global context that we're in it's as if
to me we're at a mode of being
challenged on how to actually speak
about that yeah and so it's it's kind of
an in-between state and so there's I
feel as like that the answer that you
provided is in many respects a lot of
examples that I feel I've had with some
conversations with the people here in MO
that like you know I we're talking about
it and yet we're not talking about it
and what does this mean and trying to
figure that out and you know so yeah
yeah that means that meant a lot
you know I'm thank you for your response
because it's kind of helping me to
formulate my own ideas and thoughts on
it
alright I'm glad I'm glad to hear that I
mean it's like a worthy it's a worthy
inquiry and wrestling match to be in
right now
right cuz it's like it's and I think a
lot of it has to do with our
relationship to proposition right
like you know III think I think where
where precisely gets spiritual for me or
where I have spiritual experiences is
you know there is that sense in which
you're with somebody right there's it
there when you look at in another's face
for example and you get really present
and you find you start to hear about
their lives right and you really start
to listen and there's that mutual
disclosure that starts to happen there's
a way in which there's you right and
kind of like you could say something
essential about you or your suchness
your individuality starts to reveal
itself to me but through more of a kind
of a cognitive feeling right it's like
in some way in some way in some way it's
an encounter that is is transcendent in
itself but there's also this other way
where like in in seeing who you are
there's also a way that who like that
also opens up to something much greater
right it's in is one of the things I've
noticed with always circling is that you
know somebody will open up about
something really personal to them and
they'll they'll take a risk and we'll
share something that they've they've
that's hard for them to share right and
in sharing it who they are is revealed
right beyond the content of what they
they shared like the courage or whatever
it is that's like that one that one is
hit with that sense of being moved by
someone like that is simultaneously
points to something about existence
right that we can easily start to talk
about well what is it to be moved what
is it that's moving us right like what
is it to call what what makes it worth
courage right for the sake of what and
these start to get into these very
deeply philosophical mystical spiritual
distinctions that start to open up and
that's one of the cool things about it
is that we're
this the sense of the suchness of the
person or the essence of the person and
the sense of inexhaustible
intelligibility becomes figure-ground
and at some point was circling there's
there can be this back and forth where
the figure ground starts to
interpenetrate each other and I think
it's one I think actually those kinds of
deep conversations those kinds of deep
forms of intimacy are one of the few
places that people can experience
something something beyond the secular
but in an experiential unarguable way I
think it's one of the places where we're
being is it still can still be disclosed
to us in the way in the way that it can
historically has been through like the
church and all that stuff so so I think
that is a really deep question it's a
deep inquiry and it only touches on
everything yes one ever said I'd love
the fact that you were describing what
sounded to me is a genuine attempt like
there seems as though there's a point in
which you you you you're starting to
recognize that there's something more in
that experience that you're having with
that other person and then what's coming
to my thought is kind of there's this
attuning that you're you're noting
within your being kind of thing like it
like it like you actually note kind of a
sound or a tone or something like that
and so you you're trying to connect more
with that sound and the more that you
try to do that the sound becomes even
more resonant and more harmonic and it
becomes an even fuller sound and it
makes a greater desire on your being to
want to share with that yeah more so
does that make sense oh it does make
sense and then then there's the
experience of in tuning into that sound
in it disclosing itself more to me that
allowing me to recognize it more right
at some point I start to reel
as I have become someone who could hear
that sound right and that there's a
visual closure right exactly and I think
that I though the basic fundamental unit
of relating is there's a that that's
possible right and I think circling that
leg in dialogue OHS and all the things
that we've been talking about I think is
one of the primary if not the biggest
access point to that to that kind of
spirituality for lack of a better word
that we that becomes available to us
right it's a full participatory thing
right through purchase like it's like I
know like knowing you as a participatory
event I'm a communal I'm a community
project right it's like it's a I cannot
know in relationship I cannot know you
without being known right there's a like
I I cannot hear you without being
someone who can write and - so tuning in
to those - that mutual self disclosure
that back and forth - what starts to get
revealed is something the greater or
deeper horizons that we recognize as all
that has already always the case that is
in fact having the conversation right
yeah thank you so much he did response
it exactly where I was hoping so thank
you
I guess and thank you for a time yeah
yeah thanks for pointing out the music
I'm hearing it more so Socratic skeptic
dave has posted a question guy thanks
for your YouTube channels have enjoyed
many of your videos I'm close to
developing a campfire space at the
bottom of my garden in our allotment I
want to do some kind of men's group do
you have one piece of advice for a
beginner at hosting these what
advice well well I mean so much of this
work I developed around fires at the
beach in San Francisco like with the
group of men there's something really
really ancient about that I mean I think
the biggest piece of advice is just
doing it and showing up for it there's a
setting the context right for what's
possible and what you want to occur set
in setting and then just showing up and
then and then follow the movement of
what shows all right as Heidegger would
say follow the movement of showing I
think that's most of it if he's just set
like like time-space invite the people
set your intentions and then let the
games begin
and then find what you're doing together
right and I would also say that like
that that'd be an example be like kind
of be the be the happening that you want
to have happen there so lead with your
vulnerability like share and the way
that you want to see other people share
kind of really do it in lead it from the
being mode I don't think you can go
wrong with that and then and then
afterwards make it part of it have
people tune into what right what
actually does what glowed and what
doesn't and then make that explicit
amongst a group of like oh like yeah
when we did that that seemed to really
like like zero in onto something and you
go okay well what was that like and
start to look at it like start to tune
into the music as you were saying so we
could start to hear the music so it
becomes a the process itself starts to
facilitate the the thing that you wanted
to facilitate but more of a midwifing
process listening to it
oh thanks guy that's some thoughts for
reflection on sure yeah but I think just
having the courage to put something like
that on and responding to it
wholeheartedly with your whole being
like and just being the context that you
want that you want the content to arise
inside of is the is the is is the key
hey guys thanks for coming and doing
this that's what this is Tyler Tyler
so midwifing that that's such a great
term I something we've been playing
around with lately trying to notice in
this conversational space is the kind of
the essence of masculine and feminine
energy and when it is that people are
trying to seize control or commit to a
position or hold fast and when when the
space opens up and when people relent
and when connections are made and I
think what I've really noticed is that
so much of this is typically expressed
in in deep primal relationships between
men and women between the masculine and
feminine has expressed in that sense and
the way that that's related to the types
of bonds that we seek in the the deep
compensatory aspect of the masculine and
the feminine and I wonder if there's
some quality to a different ratio of men
and women in a group that has some
effect on it or if there's some aspect
to evoking that in the presence of more
men or more women who may not
necessarily naturally come forward with
that aspect of themselves no
specifically the the aspect of
themselves that you're talking about do
you mean like do you mean like the
feminine something like the feminine
coming out in men or the masculine
coming out in women right
very Union kind of yeah animus thing
totally well you know it's funny I I
mean I don't know anything like I don't
know anything for sure about this but I
can just like look to my experience of
this is that it's always struck me that
that you know that when guys get
together they love to philosophize right
why is that I and I think it's because
actually it's one of the ways that we
actually can experience something like
burr or being pregnant with an idea or
conceiving something in that way right
that there's something there's a way
that it's like almost like in the world
like something about the domain of
philosophy starts to get at ways in
which like men can experience something
like a birth right and that kind of
energy and I've I've noticed like with
my with my wife for example like I'll
just I'm like you know I spent all day
with these questions that are burning in
me and thinking about them and reading
fucking books and having conversations
and like I'm just doing that my whole
life's about that right on some level
and it is funny like there's just a
sense with my wife like that where
she'll be like she totally gets it and
she'll go there with me but there's kind
of a sense where she already is all that
right she's she's like she already is
she's so identified with life that like
you know the the sense of the mystery
for me that's so compelling all my
attention goes there she's kind of
already the mystery right she's like
it's like embedded in her way of doing
the dishes and so there's a I think
there's a difference there right that at
least that's my experience with that but
I think something about that there
something in terms of circling and about
these practices relationally that I
think that there's something about
listening and the deep sense of
listening right that I think Socrates
always talked about is you know
listening as Midwifery right which is
the kind of listening that I noticed
that I think that that ultimately is
very connected to reverence right and in
that I think that in my experience it I
don't know if you want to call that
feminine or not but like there's
definitely a quality of proactive
quality of being able to hear not just
what you're saying but like who's saying
it and like like what isn't being said
and to start to the orient around
something being birthed that isn't fully
there yet right in an emptying and a way
of deep silence in oneself that can call
out come into prt like call out the
presence what's concealed and in reveal
in and call it into disclosure right and
that is very much I think probably the
closest thing that I ever personally get
to something like a feminine experience
no no that's perfect yeah III I mean I
experience it very much the same way and
and that's why I end up using those well
use those terms I think just because I
noticed so much of the resonance and
various aspects of my own experience and
the masculinity so I like I was I I was
there for the birth of my two children I
helped the midwives I helped pull the
children out and there's there's
something to that like the there's this
there's the struggle there's there's
this masculine struggle right it's it's
fierce it's it's energetic but then
there's also this hush there's this wait
this patient wait and then all of a
sudden there's something completely new
right like yeah that moment when it
comes out when the newness the novelty
has arrived after that pregnant period
that's just yeah so sweet yeah right and
and that that combination of the
masculine and the feminine that moment
and the product of it if you can I think
you can if you can elicit this in
conversation I think just as you said it
very much is like though it's the
procreative power in in our minds giving
birth to the tensions and struggles the
pregnancies in there that we've carried
with us for however long right and so
yeah that's that's that resonates deeply
Thanks yeah I mean you're bringing me
back to my when Forrest was born and my
my wife at that time I'll never forget
this like oh there was this point where
she was the nurses had left and her
water just broke and she's they put her
in the bathtub and all of a sudden I
went to go get something and then I come
back and all of a sudden I hear this
grown like this moan and I look over at
her and I watched I was so struck by her
because it was like it was so clear that
she was experiencing a
men dismount like more pain that I could
even imagine yet yet she was like the
moan was like where she was just kind of
digging in and like completely being
with it with it had such integrity that
and I was I looked at her and I was
struck by the experience of other Ness
I was like whatever it is that she's
doing that level of integrity was almost
like a pure kind of integrity of being
with that pain so it was such solidarity
and such like fullness or whatever it
was and I was just like I had the sense
of like man very few guys that I know
would ever sign up for that right or
could we know what we were signing up
for
and it's interesting kind of like in
that sense of that they're just
something so you know it perhaps this is
what the masculine you know what the
masculine does with the feminine is is
our love for them in some way kind of
birds out right in them like when our
consciousness is really really centered
and really clear and in a certain sense
we open our consciousness to them and we
see them and we love them so deeply that
on some level I think what happens is
they they bird into appearance they bird
into adornment they glow and glisten
right and the more that they glow and
glisten right the more my consciousness
has to expand in order for their
appearance to fully blossom so there's a
and it's interesting now to think about
this right if I think about it now of
like well what is it that's happening in
in like a in like a conversation my wife
is just giving me the thumbs up in a
heart thing on her chest
she's crying now um that there's if we
look at that like okay so what's
happening with the love of an idea when
it when a when a distinction or a
something about a dynamic or an idea is
being disclosed right like if we say on
some level that my listening is a giving
burst that to that right there is a
certain kind of like it's funny I think
it really is it's like this experience
of being fully engaged in that way of
giving birth and it's just interesting
to think about that like I do think it's
one of the ways that we get to
experience that birth this morning I
just wanted to share that synchronicity
and I know it's Cruz mythology up but
she's naming my nephew Odin welcome Odin
so church fire Ethan has a question in
text chat are you familiar with the
International Institute of restorative
practices I took a course last year and
they had an emphasis on a similar
practice that they called circling to
use in a classroom setting but your name
never came up is your method different
from theirs and are they are they taking
your copy right yeah I've never I've
never heard of them yeah I've never
heard of them so I really can't answer
that well I guess I guess there are
other Institute's that that do there are
other organizations that do claim to to
do circling you consider circling
proprietary do you mind if other people
use the term if they're not in
conjunction conjunction with you or you
don't have to answer if you don't like
that's a whole left brain
right now I'm contending with that a lot
right now and I think that the way that
we're working at it because it's been a
you know it it's it's there's a whole
set of distinctions around it but we're
basically kind of looking at a way to to
preserve circling right and in a way
such that people know when they're
getting it and so like what what
organization and what way to do that is
all what we're in the process of you
know trying to do right now because it's
been a it's been like circling is spread
like crazy and on the other hand
circling is very difficult to do well
and so there's a there's a way where I
like that it spread so much and then
there's a way where I'm just hearing
people call circling like to me doesn't
look at all sound anything like circling
so there's a there's a sweet spot in
there that I'm that we're working out
anything in particular that you'd like
to point out that's the wrong way to do
circling something like a common mistake
made huh yeah well I think here's here's
one of the things right and I think it's
also a bigger issue but I do think I
want emphasizes that circling is not
therapy and I think that one of the
things the things that really kind of
troubles me a lot is when I I hear
people talk about like that you know
what word when I heard when I hear the
word people talk about trauma and
working with trauma and circling and
like these kind of mishmash and kind of
therapeutic kinds of sensibilities and
with it it starts to really look like no
that's not what circling is right sir
circling isn't psychology in fact you
could say that like circling is a I
think it's a philosophical
phenomenological practice right where
it's more about the revealing of
what of what is and it's so it's so I
think the the issue is is that like a
lot of times that people find that
really healing and they find it really
therapeutic but but there's a real big
difference between trying to do that or
trying to invoke something like healing
or therapy and just doing the practice
right and going into that space so
that's that's one of them is like is it
when you're when you're circling
somebody's like the one of the big no
nose is kind of giving advice or or
trying to get something to happen it's
more like what we want to do is really
open up to what is happening and seeing
how close we can get to what's happening
and then notice what happens as we get
closer to it and there's other things
too like that you know you don't want to
give advice right you don't want to be
fixing people you don't want to be
trying to heal therapy or correct people
or kind of like impose your like your
values onto somebody it's all the things
that what you want to do is circling is
just deeply getting intimate with what
is as it reveals itself to you well if I
can forget a follow-up to that
I mean if somebody is circling and often
what is in our heads is dealing with
whatever stressors we have or things
like trauma or psychological issues that
we have but that may be what somebody's
feeling in the moment how do you
recommend you recommend disclosing those
things not disclosing or doing and how
do you do it in a non therapeutic way
well it's interesting guys do we go well
here's the thing about it is that is it
I think that like like when you're when
you really be with something it can be
really therapeutic right so there's a
sense of like yeah like as we go in to
ask you like well what's what's going on
with you right and then just maybe one
layer of
is is is the situation that you're
thinking about and then we just kind of
get really present to what that
situation means to you right and as we
dive in there right you're like you may
hit some sadness you may hit some grief
and we just keep welcoming whatever's
there as it reveals itself to us and how
it reveals like what happens into the
space between I just actually I just
posted a on my channel a couple of
videos back earlier this week I just
posted a a pretty good videotaped circle
as a demo circle that I did for in the
art of circling program which is a
year-long training that I do it's a it's
a pretty well it's circling is difficult
to catch on film but this one does a
pretty good job and it's a pretty like
it's a pretty profound circle and you
can really get the sense of just kind of
diving really really deep in with this
person and and just being with what is
and more of what is just started to
disclose and her whole life was at it
alright I want to be
but for your time we're coming up to
about an hour and we started later are
you are you okay - keep going did you
want to yeah I can go right
I can go for another probably 10 minutes
or so sure anyone else want to either
ask a question or give an experience
interacting it in some way I kind of had
a question that came up when we had a
kind of mini demonstration here with
people that had had partaken in circling
before and there was some effect i
noticed from one of the facilitators
that to me at least felt like a kind of
bending of the interpretation of a
person's response towards a positive
effect and i'm assuming that this was
kind of a way to create perhaps a
certain feeling over what the practice
was inducing and one of the questions
that came up is in the practice of
circling is is there kind of this
orientation of in some sense trying to
move away from our tendency to affect
certain observations or is there this
kind of perhaps more directed sense to
it you partially answered this in your
last couple ones but i wanted to kind of
highlight that specific area i think
well let's see see here's the thing
about it is that there's what we're
talking about is like a relational it's
like a relational practice right so
right it's there's what like there's
what's going on with you and then
there's what's like going on with me as
well as it's happening right so there's
a way where if the circle if you know if
the circle is structured where we're
just circling one person and everyone's
attention is on it right really the
place that you want to come from is just
really like seeing what's what's
happening and and then getting is close
to what what's all there is human
possible you want to like you want to
like eat and what's what's interesting
about it right is is it in relationship
you know we say the practice is like the
practice of being with what is or as I
like to say of dwelling in the question
how deeply can we and how profoundly can
we be with what is well is in
relationship is like the moment I see it
the moment you bring language to it it's
disclosed there's also the moment that
it somehow changes often right so
there's an evolving disclosure that
happens with it and what we want to do
is we want to tune into and be attuned
by that whatever that movement of
disclosure is it it's funny because it's
it's interesting I've noticed this with
that I think one of the ways it gets
like one of the things that kind of gets
in the way of circling a lot of times is
this very kind of atomistic sense about
the present moment right where there's a
sense there's a sense in which right if
we just talk about what's here right now
right as if like as if like the the
moment was a dot right and then the next
moment is another dot or something like
that right I think totally misses the
the the ontology of how temporal
temporality how temporal we are through
and through so for example like what may
be present for you is this this this
tension in your shoulder and that's
what's like that's the thing that you
can sense it you can feel but then if I
go okay well what's all involved in that
tension right what will usually find is
is a whole future that I'm anticipating
embracing myself for and like then what
we find it's like if we unfold that that
tension in your shoulders even more what
just gets discloses like what has been
anticipated maybe a whole history right
that
embedded in the concerns in which is is
is this current note is the tension in
my shoulders but just like music I don't
hear music by listening to each note
Etta mystically I actually I only hear
music precisely when the note points to
the future and the past notes that just
went on and I can start to hear the
melody right that's it that's the that's
the thing we want to do is revealing
more of the music that's being played in
a certain sense right and that's the
beautiful description of the
phenomenology that I was experiencing
even within our little attempt to get a
feel for it yeah we're in many ways it
was by hyper in some sense hyper
focusing on that moment that it seemed
to expand into almost a narrative unto
itself you could feel history and go
yeah bingo blossoming forth through that
exact moment
right I was like well what else what
what the hell else are we other than at
like a moment of the world disclosing
itself through and as us right like so
if you go deep enough into somebody's
issue you if you just keep following
that thread eventually you're just gonna
hit God right like it's that and I think
that's what what where it starts to get
mystical and and where it makes a lot of
sense to describe circling in this kind
of spiritual language right is is
precisely it's that quality of
attentiveness to the phenomena of God
because when you think about it every
we're so it's so it's so intense being
human I think about it I could actually
this is a good this is a good
exploitation of this when I was in art
school
I graduated for the terrace gardens to
to I'm a painter and a sculptor and I
had this art teacher that was in a life
drawing class that I had for a number of
years in a row so he was really good it
was so
funny to hear him talk about the
difficult D in capturing the human form
and what you used to say is like there's
it's so difficult to render either
abstractly or expressively or or or or
literally representationally because
there is not one part of the human form
that isn't dynamic and expressive and
another way of saying that is that
there's not one inch of us that isn't a
communication right that everything is
expressing like for us we are we are
creatures of language right INRI are
constantly like emanating and imbued
with levels and layers of
intelligibility most of which we're not
even aware of but all of it is a
communication right so on some level
when you tune into you would be I mean
the levels of the levels of complexity
and depth of what you can begin to hear
if you really start to a tune to the
depth of what it really is to be a human
being and this is what's interesting is
like I think I can only tune into the
level like the deepest level of your
humanity oh I could only tune tune into
that with my own humanity right and so
that kind of quality or that observation
of like yeah the more we tune into this
the more there's almost like a like a
narrative stretch unfold from itself
right from the phenomena like that it
but if you think about like the way you
stand as then unfolding happens though
like what you start to all the micro
instinctive movements and your nervous
system that you make the attune again
does facial expressions the clike how
you stretch in certain ways in in in
becoming a part of all that I think are
is the machinery right that affords us
being open to the world in a radical way
it's interesting the image or one point
that kind of popped up in my my head as
you were describing there was having
mystical experience in relation with
others
having this sense of almost those those
micro expressions that deep connection
to the thing in some sense animating the
the object actually started to blur such
that the object itself was likewise the
expression underneath or part of that
thing that animates fundamentally and in
some sense it felt like a deep blurring
between the kind of ontological pursuit
and the theological pursuit and it I
don't know it's like it moved me out of
a naive aesthetic frame I have a
helicopter in the background sorry it
moved me out of that naive aesthetic
sense of someone's physical existence as
somehow representative
of some aspect of beauty and instead
that sense of beauty seemed to be in the
existence that was there at all I don't
have a good I don't have good language
anymore but that was good and what how
would you say the process of seeing that
right and then read ascribing it like
what did that do to you if it did
anything who did you mean become in
order to to see that right what did that
take on your behalf
well it's interesting flipping it back
inside because it had such a deep kind
of mirroring effect in that it likewise
felt like I was experiencing myself as
the object within the subject see I'm
again losing every language yeah
well notice notice okay so just like
right there notice cognitively the
stretch that you're needing to make in
order to describe this experience that
you had right that that stretch right
it's precisely the practice I think
great disability like for example right
there just a math thing okay
I don't I described something that's
needed like both subject and object
mirroring each other as it's happening
like like just feel all the different
capacities you're trying to balance and
just in your cognition and describing
that like I think that is the that's the
thing that the circling opens one -
right right right
and yeah in that sense there's there's
this kind of deep realization that I
can't actually capture the thing outside
of existing itself yes and here's that
here's what's really interesting this is
where it starts to mirror into the in
the Socratic dialogue right where
there's paradox of of the dialogues
where here Socrates will like say okay
what is what is this virtue and then
it's just that like the whole the whole
ride is this frustrating thing where you
find out at the end
like not even Socrates knows what the
answer to that question is yet somehow
at the end of the conversation there's
this openness that somehow the dialogue
had reached a level of aporia that
transcended the dialogue itself and
that's me he started to like the like
the dialogue allowed us to begin to
circle around and noticing a kind of
disclosure of what was already the case
that we realized in not being able to
put into language we realized that we
walking away from that our eyes our
vision is better our listening is deeper
you know is like people want you want to
send your sons to go spend time with
Socrates it's a it said I think
that that's that is the possibility
that's open in relationship and dialogue
that is one level it's really really old
but it's it's it's latent and it's
possible I think that's what I think
it's that sensibility that even draws us
to this dialogue that we're having right
now it's very exciting it is yes and
thank you much that was a wonderful bit
of conversation I'll open it back up
yeah I just I just I just got just to
let you know I just got a text and my
client is needing to cancel last minute
so I actually have time oh sure well
we'll take it curious what is the what
is the the one who's hosting the meeting
what's what are you getting what are you
here what's what's striking you what's
the well you're talking about reverence
was very interesting to me
you know reverence is I didn't I think I
have a discomfort with the concept of
reverence you know that maybe it strikes
me from the the religious aspect that it
you know that it seems different from
you know respect or you know
appreciation that reverence seems to be
you know giving up something to the to
the the other the other side so I I
found that that interesting I guess the
way I sort of reconciled it in my head
is its reverence of the apprec--
reverence of the communication between
the two people yeah that that that I I
think I could i can sign sign on for
that there's it's the communication
itself we're reviewing yeah the
disclosure the living disclosure that's
happening and the process that we're in
you could you can as you imagine that is
it fair to say that you can see you can
feel whatever organ that Revere's you
can feel that or gonna be able to open
up to that
yeah and the just the yeah exposing I
guess you opening yourself up to the
communication in the way that you
haven't before and valuing it for itself
right right
yeah yeah what is it like to think yeah
what is that like for you to just kind
of think about that and ponder it and
well I know there's something exciting
for me always in in having a good
conversation when you get into sort of a
flow state where you're where you're say
even an argument with somebody who you
disagree with but where you're really
communicating where you're really
understanding one another where and
maybe you come to some realization or
you or one of you realizes something in
the other person's arguments or vice
versa and there there's an ecstatic
feeling that I times get in those kind
of discussions and then what do you
making that that ecstatic feeling what
do you make of that what what affords
that or what is it about what does that
say about conversation that that one of
the things that lets you know that
you're in one like that is is that you
start to get you can feel a really
ecstatic and in this flow state what do
you make about what do you make it up
well I think that we have there you know
I you know when I before I started the
server some of my work sort of on
Twitter my pet projects and Twitter was
promoting productive discussions and I
would try it you know Twitter
discussions for example are very
unproductive and you know sort of
garbage fiery like but I would have some
good discussions with people and they
would say you know what this was the
first time I've actually had a
productive discussion and and they there
is a certain delight there and I think
they're people don't realize how
rewarding it is to really communicate
with somebody and we get into these
us-versus-them dichotomies and yeah and
we really get caught up in them and it's
hard to get rid of it but once you do
even with you know when you have a great
discussion with them
that reading it brings you it brings
them closer to us and your understanding
them better and there's something great
about that and I think there's there's
an untapped desire I think that many
people have and they don't realize they
have that desire all right great until
they have that experience and they're
like wow that was great I don't fight
right there's something inherently is it
fair to say there's something innately
when you have those conversations where
that you're describing it's like there's
something encouraging about it right yes
it's like it's it's one of those things
I noticed this about like I think it's
well on the same level of doing a loosen
to Jen's right like I always had this
experience of like when I would do a
loosen to Jen where I would start like
it would start to come on and I'd feel
the shift in my consciousness and
usually like my first thought would be
oh shit it happened again
when I was thinking about dropping this
acid or doing these mushrooms or
whatever like I thought I was actually
thinking about this but now I remember
like oh this is now I was not
representing this at all
now I remember this right there's a
quality of like like there's knowing it
and then there's getting it right and
this experience of like when you enter
in that space I have yet and I've done
like I don't know I probably I
calculated at one point I think I've led
something like 8,000 circles right in my
life and whenever that thing happens
it's always like that it's always like
this existential oh yeah right like
there's something about it that cannot
be represented right it but it's a
living idea it's a living sense of a
sense of what's possible becomes felt in
that that that felt sense of possibility
I think is the standing out that one
feels which is what ecstasy is right to
stand out from while being in and I
think until
somebody's had it they don't necessarily
even though they they want it when it
comes to communicating with other people
right totally totally and here's the
thing about it is like one of the things
I've noticed is that I really do think
that like listening does it there's I
see a lot of I see a lot of books on
communication right and I see a lot a
lot of literature on it right as there
is there ought to be but usually what
it's talking about are like it's all
it's usually talking about ways of
talking right ways of expressing
yourself ways of saying things and I
think one of the one of the big the big
things that kind of gets forgotten is
that there is no speech without a
listening right that ontologically
right there's a sense in which it's hard
to imagine like first they were speaking
and then somebody listened well what
calls forth the speech right unless
there's a listener there so this sense
of this sense of listening is so deep to
all of our communications but it's one
of those it's one of the things that I
don't hear much attention being given to
it but like you know if somebody like
you know you can take the clip like the
most closed person and then you just
start getting interested in what has
them be so closed right what hasn't
think the way that they think and you
lean into them and you you listen to
them you listen to - to the sense of
them being a legitimate other there is
something that in people I've noticed
that just innately responds to that
right with self-disclosure we're almost
designed to do that I think on some
level so there's that I think one of the
things I really appreciate about
circling is this deeper to admit and
this focus on to genuine what is it to
genuinely listen to someone what is to
genuinely as Heidegger would say you
know maybe it's a good idea that we can
hear things that are beyond what I
already think
because they think that there is what
becomes possible and listening at John
and I talked a lot extensively about
this a lot in their last video a few
days ago um I really appreciated it and
it was this sense of like listening when
you think about what listening really is
I think people usually think of it as
like well listening is just being kind
of an emptiness right that that is
filled with words on some level but
that's not listening at all like if you
think about it as I'm talking right now
especially like of the people listening
to me at some point you'll probably
throughout this conversation you'll
probably have like drifted and started
thinking about something else and then
you notice like oh shit
like you you pop out of that thought and
you realize you hadn't listened for the
last minute there's a it shit that
reveals this very very close
relationship between thought and
listening that it's I can't I can't
listen and think at the same time so
there's this way in which when I listen
right in some way I'm in a certain sense
I'm allowing another to think a thought
in me right that's kind of what
listening is now what's really
interesting is that when you think about
that like this is why I think for me I
would have to say that I've just been so
fortunate in this regard since the young
age I've just had people older older
people who have just taken me under
their wing and and in some ways they
would speak to me like they would speak
to me on some innate level like what
made them mentors for me is that they
knew that like for for them to speak to
me that in order for me to listen that
something profound would be happening in
that listening that would be that that
that that spoke to who I was and spoke
to who I could become so there's this
there's this way and I think probably
everyone on this array everyone on this
list probably has like a bent towards
both the spiritual but also the
philosophical the the the in election
right and I would imagine we all know
that experience of like like grappling
with the text ray or an author or
somebody who thinks is saying something
to you but you can't it's just outside
of your ability to comprehend but you're
drawn towards it so you draw it into
listening now there's some thoughts in
order for me to think them I can't think
them standing on my own on my own like
presuppositions I need to act in order
to think the thought that I can kind of
sense is there's a lot there I must in
some sense stand on a different set of
presuppositions in order to understand
what you're saying
like that's we're listening and as you
start to shift your presuppositions you
start to shift who you are how you
understand and this is where I think
listening becomes really can become
really transformative and in many ways
it's like I kind of feel like myself
like on some level I feel like I'm like
constituents I'm constitutive by all of
the profound relationships and
conversations I've ever had in my entire
life including the ones that went badly
fun I'm most fucked up by all the
relationships that didn't go well right
so so that that issue of the the
mind-wandering do you have any tips for
how you keep your attention focused on
the other person how you really take it
in without losing it yeah well I think
one of the I mean one of them is just
like first of all it's just having that
intention like having the intention and
being transparent to yourself with the
intention of like I really want to hear
you I really want to get what you're
saying and then some practical ways of
doing that is just simple simply kind of
like exercises of just simple
paraphrasing like before you speak like
summarizing what you just heard right
like like like like right now like you
wanted to so you so you're you're what
I'm hearing is that you have an eye on a
practical matter that like it's not
always easy to listen to people so how
do I begin to do that what are
practical things that I can do to
actually do that did I get it
yes exactly yeah so one of the things I
like about paraphrasing as an exercise
is that it it's it's similar to mimicry
I think it's a lot more profound than
just repeating what you heard it's
actually when you paraphrase somebody
you're actually in a certain sense
becoming them and taking a walk with
what they just said and there's
something that happens in that walk that
like speaking it actually manually has
you think what they just said out and at
the end of that thought there's kind of
a little sense of like oh you just went
on a ride and then you can you can start
to notice whatever you say next will be
in direct relationship to what they just
said hmm
I think there's something about there's
like that you can look at that is like
an asana right of like really making
sure that you kind of repeat back what
you heard before you say the next thing
that's one way of doing it excellent I
don't
focus of everything does every does
anyone else want to jump in and yeah we
fact it like I'd love to hear what you
guys are hearing what you're getting so
this last work well at the start of the
conversation i i sensed an attempt at an
engendering of enthusiasm and I sense it
again but it was I wasn't really there
in the middle of the conversation apart
from some genuine enthusiasm against but
so it is that something that you're
you're trying to play with like creating
like an atmosphere for for fertile
relationship or and and and do you have
like strategies of relating to that well
I think it's kind of like I'm not sure
if this is what you're asking but I'll
see if I can if I can if my answer to
let's like let me know if I answer the
question that you're talking about so
see what I have to say like one of the
things I've noticed in just in my own
experience is like my my temperament is
naturally not extroverted right I would
have to say I'm like more on the
introverted side so I often times write
this is and this is where it's so
interesting because in a certain sense
being committed to developing circling
that commitment has drawn me out to more
relationship that I would have I
wouldn't have naturally I would I
wouldn't have naturally preferred so I
think you guys all know this like it's
like where if you're in a bad mood you
don't feel like talking but you have an
appointment or something or like there's
like you committed to go to your
friend's birthday party and you're
feeling depressed or something like that
there's this kind of hump you have to
get over but then once you once you
start to engage in the dialogue where
you go to the party
like there's there at some point like
oftentimes what what I found that
happens at some point I surrender my
will right over to the ritual of the
relationship or the conversation and at
some point I find it's become in the the
realm of the always already I'm all
already always it caught into the flow
of the conversation I can't tell you how
many times it's been it's well here's
the thing it's like it's like it there's
a there's a you could you could look at
conversations as like a ritual right and
so like when you have commitments that
have you go beyond your preferences I've
this is one of the big things about
relationships I've notices that in some
sense like just getting yourself in
front of people and becoming involved
there's something about the the economy
the conversation starts to catch right
and I find myself like someone who's
having the conversation and I want to
and I get into a flow so I think like I
think you know we could show up we can
show up to a conversation with that
intention without necessarily having to
feel like it which is often the case for
me right so that that's that's really
nice so so how do you decide what to do
do you think like the end like
experiential things are you like
attuning to some kind of tone that you
sends out there like yeah it's much it's
I always say that there's a you know
it's interesting it's it's so it's so
interesting to think about this because
it's so a match
imagine you're you know you you're
you're alone in a room right just by
yourself and then just bring like
somebody in the room and just sit there
sitting in the quarter
that's a completely different room all
right
like versus when you're alone and then
when there's someone else there there's
such an there is such an embodied
socially embedded beyond ourselves thing
that happens when we're around other
people so there's just a matter of just
could - getting yourself involved where
there are things going on in your body
and your social makeup that will just
naturally be attuned and be attuned by
that that that that somebody else is
there right so I think there's just
natural machinery that just just works
on its own so half of I think most of it
is just showing up and then the other
part is just like just I would say
really bringing my interest to what
other people are saying and what the
conversation is and manually bringing my
attention there and at some point as
they bring my attention they're just
kind of like with meditation right you
bring your attention back you know like
when you start thinking you lose contact
with your breasts and in a moment you
you catch it you Bruce bring yourself
back I think it's like it's something's
very similar in being caught in a
dialogue right just bringing yourself
back and showing up at some point a
dialogue and especially really deep
dialogues right in some sense you become
a self the the you yourself becomes
given by dialogue and that's where we
start to get into dialogue oh so in a
lot of these conversations that we've
been talking about but I think it's like
it's very similar to where where you
bring your attention and so bringing
your attention to like your your in your
interest to who this person is and what
they're saying and like even if you
don't feel like it even if you don't
feel the interest right
bringing kind of coming out of yourself
and bringing your interest there like is
a way of letting letting the process
catch you
how's that no that that's great yeah I'm
I'm also playing with these things and
I'm trying to figure out some some
orientation so it's always nice to hear
other people yeah
explain the process totally anyone else
and yeah what else are you guys hearing
how many people are here twenty
twenty-one right now Oh
twenty-one right on the question I've
already spoken a lot so I don't want to
step on anyone else mm-hmm well well I'm
sure they'll scream if you start
stepping so let me just go ahead and
start stepping okay I want to reverse
the polarity of my first question where
I asked about scaling up yeah
instead do you have any thoughts on
applying this to our own internal
dialogue and how we interact with
ourself just also to say you've talked a
lot about what we can learn about
ourselves and grow in relationship do
you feel about self development and
extended periods of isolation yeah well
I would you know I would say that I mean
what you're pointing to is a real deep
thing right you know it's it you could
almost say that we're always in a
dialectic right of some kind with
ourselves with our environment and like
even when we're thinking worth like
we're thinking that thought has some
sense of somebody who's hearing the
thought right or someone who's thinking
I think really it's it's arguable but I
would say that like it's it's safe to
say that like we're a relationship all
the way down and I'm constantly talking
to people in my head
right even when they're not there like
for example
this is a great example I think in Cory
an x book which I just I just uploaded
another video on Cory anton who wrote a
book called cellphone authenticity which
is kind of a an existential hi to Gary
and reassessment of the self and then
from that reassessment what is what
would what does that imply for
authenticity it's really love this I
love that guy so we go deep into this
well any things he says in this book
that I just thought was just hilarious
and ironically funny was he you know
imagine you know you can imagine an
artist who does the greatest masterpiece
of his life and then when he's done he
imagines other people seeing it and
criticizing it so he destroys the
painting the question is is did he avoid
that did he avoid the criticism I think
you got to answer no he didn't write in
it in the end that there's this way and
it starts to highlight that like I am
social all the way through like even
when I'm alone right there are embedded
social practices in the in the way that
this the the agent or an arena
relationship show up is is imbued with
people even if they didn't ever
criticize me that I destroyed the
painting so that they wouldn't
presupposes that I've I was already I
already was criticized by them right I
didn't need them to criticize me and so
that just kind of gets it how deep it is
so I would say that like that we're
always in dialog intimate dialogue with
ourselves and that there's that there's
there's a way of of being one of the
ways of having reverence for yourself
and respecting yourself is to is to give
attention to that dialogue and I know
that like in working in my coaching
practice and working with people one of
the biggest places that I think that
we're really fused right the self is
really fused as to the super-ego right
or that sense of
that sense of that that that critical
voice that often like its job is to kind
of keep you the same right which is
really about your survival and how it
lives is this kind of this this constant
sense of criticism that comes up
whenever you start to go beyond the
shape you normally take and I notice
that like in when I'm working with
people coaching them you know they start
to set goals and they start to do they
go they start to move towards what they
who they aspire to be and it neva
tebron's up all that self judgment and
criticism and so one of the big
relationships that they start to get
into is to start to see that that's
happening oh there's a structure at me
that's like basically telling me what
reality is and who you are and what I
can and can't do and Who am I to dare to
even think I could do that and all of
that like all of that that process and
so a big part of realizing and going to
that next level of who they are is about
having a real relationship with that for
what it is and going into dialogue with
it right disengaging from it like
hearing the way that it talks to you and
the way that you positioned yourself and
fight with it and avoid it and that's
like an example of like seeing the
dialogues that are always going on
inside of ourselves so yeah some
personality model I'm sorting myself out
was mentored under Roger strucken and
Reinhold Sabol he specializes in doing
some personality would love to hear you
have a conversation with someone an
expert on the submarine circling when
you dissect yourself into a variety of
sub
what they work people through seems very
similar in a lot of ways what you have
people do with each other
totally totally yeah yeah
I am all like I am like even when I'm
alone I am only myself in relationship
to another right like it's it's kind of
like ontological II that's what itself
is it's it's always an agent and arena
it's a deep struck it's like in the
structure of our being so I think all
those kind of techniques are really
great that kind of work with
subpersonalities and have you go into
dialogue with them it just seems to just
make explicit what's already going on
right so I think it can be really
helpful to break that stuff up right and
to you know actually have each part of
you complete a sentence with the other
part and you get in a dial if things is
resolved just on their own that same
kind of moving to another level through
you know conversation basically with
yourself all all things that facilitate
that just seem like like no brainer
that's good and it's also you know it's
interesting to like I think one of the
ways that people often you know
encircling it well if you notice like we
like if you get to know somebody you
start to eat like everyone has rants
that they get on - right will you be
talking to them and all of a sudden
they're just like they're addressing
some concern that you didn't have with
them about something and they start to
talk to somebody else it's almost like
they're taking one of the these people
in their head and then they're kind of
putting it on you and then talking to
you um encircling seems to bring that
out a lot like where like for example
I'll give it one example of somebody I
was working with for a long time where
he he came in he came in he we started
talking and and and I started to notice
that he kept saying this particular
sentence structure over and over over
again he kept saying he would say
something and you say I yeah but it's
cool it's all right and then he talked
about something else and at the end of
it he say oh that you know it's cool but
it's okay it's okay
and I
like counting about 30 times that he
said that he finally was like can I ask
you who you're talking to and he's like
what what do you mean and I was like
well you've reassured me that it's cool
and it's okay like 30 times and I never
insinuated that it wasn't cooler okay
and all of a sudden he's like he stops
and his eyes get really big and he's
like who was I talking to and then over
the next year we discover that actually
who he's talking to he had no idea like
his whole like what happened in his
childhood and his parents were insane
and his mother was hospitalized and then
he was like kind of holding his whole
child he was like the savior for
everybody and he had no real
conceptualization of that or awareness
of that yet that he would kind of index
his world in terms of that history and
then try to solve it and so like that's
an example of like where where we
actually and oftentimes encircling where
people will be sharing or talking and
people feel disconnected and oftentimes
what starts to happen is we look at that
we go it's like okay so what was
happening in that moment and oftentimes
what will happen is people will realize
like oh they weren't talking to us at
all they were assuming that like I
didn't you guys didn't like me and
therefore I was kind of already kind of
anticipating that and trying to please
you right and it wasn't actually in
connection to the people there so like
when you start to get into an exam and
like well when when there's a loss of
connection or the lack of connection and
then you you highlight that and you get
curious and like start to unpack that a
bit what you find are those kinds of
internal relationships that we project
out it's not
the person who flips you off on the
street or whatever that's often not
about you at all it's just you're not
mad at me you're still mad at your dad
or whatever yeah going around
interacting with the world in such a way
that they're just projecting their own
things onto it and interacting with that
totally yeah totally
absolutely absolutely it's kind of like
one of the big openings right you know
talking about listening to really listen
to somebody in some senses is is you
know a teacher of mine that that said
like ask me is like okay in order for
listening to be available right to you
for genuine listening to happen what do
you have to understand about listening
such that if you don't understand this
listening is impossible
right and we Pete we were in a he lived
in it like a an area that had like a
town square with a park in the center of
it and we were like walking along and
and I would give him I don't know some
smart answer about it and he's like nope
give it another shot and so he walked
around the park like three times and
he's like he stops me and says okay you
ready it's like what do you got to get
about listening such that if you don't
get this listening is it possible he
stops and he looks at me and he's like
you got to get that you don't listen and
he's and all of a sudden they started to
sink in is like oh yeah like what I have
to get about listening is that I don't
listen because if I can't hear that I
don't listen right
listening is impossible but the moment I
hear that I wasn't hearing you that I
was hearing my projection of you or all
my pre listenings of you all my
judgments of you or whatever the moment
I can begin to hear that is the moment
genuine listening becomes possible and I
keep hearing I keep getting that on a
deeper and deeper level myself like I
always like because I never think when
I'm listening that I'm not listening
I always think that I'm listening when
I'm listening but like but then I'll
start to hear like oh shit
I actually wasn't hearing you but I just
heard that I wasn't hearing you is the
moment I begin to hear you it's sort of
like meditation when you realize your
mind is wandering very much like
meditation I think I think that's why
circling oftentimes is is referred to as
a is an inner subjective meditation
anyone else want to share what they've
taken from the conversation today well I
wasn't actually gonna say anything but
what was just said about not listening
that was very interesting to me and I
was wondering if there's any techniques
for kind of helping other people have
that realization that that they're not
really that they're listening to
somebody who is not there or that is in
their head rather than the person who's
right in front of them trying to
communicate with them all right well I
think it's like I mean one thing just on
this end I think it back to just saying
what you heard right so just having like
like really really saying saying okay
this is what he heard and telling him
what you heard and then finding out
whether or not you heard him right like
is that what they met great and so
that's one way right of just not
assuming that I'm hearing you but
actually checking right because I have
to say there's so many working with like
lots of couples in marriage counseling
like most of the time when people are
arguing they're not arguing about the
same thing and they don't hear that
that's so like a lot of a lot of the
coaching is just having them start to
hear what they're actually saying to
each other and then having them hear
that they weren't hearing it I mean when
it comes to somebody else it's mostly
like you can I think you can ask them
like so like what are you hearing I just
want to make sure that we're like you're
hearing what I'm saying or I just want
to get it right and you can invite them
just speak it out right where where you
make the listening u11 is you
unconcealed listening and he's
you acknowledge there is a listening
that could happen here right and it's
kind of what what this conversation is
inside of and it it could it could
happen in greater or lesser degrees and
to tuning to the listening and then
bringing it up as part of the
conversation that's something that's
really rare but it's I think it's always
valid to do I've got something to add
here I've been this has been a recent
epiphany of mine the whole how to have a
good conversation thing I'm happy to
share I'm happy to pause I tend to get
into monologues but I've learned
recently how to stop doing that well oh
my point of view on this is roughly that
the best way to have a good conversation
is to shut the fuck up I'm sorry for
being blunt but it's the truth my father
unfortunately he has a different problem
my brother has the problem of not being
able to shut his mouth my father and
these are both major triggers for my own
hypomania well I'll leave it at that but
my father has a problem of not being
able to hear and it's not that his ear
his ears have problems is that his ears
aren't open whereas I'm now all ears I
have nothing but ears my I don't even
have eyes anymore and with my father
what I noticed there's a pattern that
he's gotten into he's built a gutter in
his mind a gutter that the bowling ball
just wants to fall into the more that
you build through this gutter you till
this line he becomes easier and easier
to fall into it he found a wife that
adapted fully to him well she would
English she learned his culture she
moved to the Middle East I'm gonna end
the monologue but for my father his
problem is that he asks direct questions
and he asked them an infinite number of
times because he doesn't respect your
time he doesn't respect my time he just
thinks that you'll solve the problem for
him so he never had to hear because you
will solve the problem for him after 50
question if you ask the same question
three times or 30 times
eventually the other person is going to
get frustrated and then they're gonna
stop talking they're gonna either do it
for your stop talking to you so I think
these are the two things one is shutting
up listening like literally opening your
ears you'll find that you attract people
to you when you do this you'll attract
muses people that don't speak for months
maybe maybe they observe you and then
you'll find a creative spark that opens
up the door to many more epiphanies yeah
totally
and that speaks to just I think what
you're talking about is it that speaks
to the primacy of listening right there
yeah there's a way in which you can
listen so deeply that somebody can begin
to speak more deeply right in you could
say the openness in which you're
listening takes place and thinking about
this yesterday I was working with a
client who is with another teacher and
he was taught she's talking about like
he's writing emails to him that she
finds herself using language in a new
way when she types to him and and the a
way that she's really like impressed
with and proud of herself afterwards
she's like oh wow I can't believe that I
kind of came up with that and in a
certain sense that was in the context of
his sense of listening that she
literally became someone and spoke in
new ways that was in some way speaking
into a listening so like listening is a
it's not just an empty it's not it's
never just an empty space right it's a
generative it generates
speech it's this it's the it's the space
in which speech is disclosed into in
fact I would even say like some of the
best thinking ray is is I really learned
this from Heidegger in a big way because
he talks a lot about this that there's
like this kind of this deep wedded miss
between listening and thought that that
you know I think the best beach
comes out of where you are tuning into
something and and you're listening
you're listening is just is right before
what you're about to say it's like
you're listening to what is being
thought right a moment and then you
speak it right after where there's a
listening and speaking that is comes via
the listening even to yourself and what
you're saying right what wants to be
thought I think that's really like
that's where genuine thinking really
comes from is is kind of like we hear
what wants to be thought we hear us like
a glistening of an intelligibility that
doesn't have words yet but we can hear
it and we can begin to bring it to
speech and we find out what it is that
we think through revealing what we're
hearing through our speech I think
that's the sweet spot we're listening
and and listening and speaking and
thinking become like almost the same
event that's like flow state stuff I can
definitely relate with that and I
definitely don't want to jump on anyone
who would like to add but you know I
actually believe not you know that's it
that's a that's a crush to say that to
get a little meta but you know I would
say that I've solved the meta crisis the
crisis of the sense making apparatus and
I believe you've touched on it I
resonate deeply with what you just said
if I can offer a tool that you might use
in the future to convey your
understanding your listening skills one
of them is to just relay it back very
simply in their own words literally copy
their words if you don't know what they
said literally just say verbatim what
they said back to them they'll correct
it and then if you want to get a little
bit more advanced you might say it back
to them more concisely with more
concision
like a surgeon and if you want to do
even better you'll do what I just did
repeat yourself use different words
different tone and then draw an analogy
make it visceral I just drew your your
mind if you have an internal monologue
which many of you don't
to stabbing and blood and now when you
think of concise you're gonna think of
blood maybe perhaps perhaps not the
confusion is good too because when you
confuse people you open their brains to
programming actually to reprogramming
because they're already in a cult many
cults and you want them to be in cults
that are productive for them and their
families and so they they need sense
making apparatus they don't have it
they've it's been programmed out of them
as a baby you have this it's literally
just listening to the environment their
ears are born open when we close them
intentionally or maybe unintentionally
but it's definitely negligence
it's definitely abuse and what I've
learned is that just literally by
opening your ears all of your senses and
listening to the environment it tells
you everything you need to know because
people reflect back into the environment
when you speak you hear your words it's
not for you when I'm speaking to you
it's for me because I'm teaching myself
how to say it better next time I'm
teaching myself what's important and
what's not and when you ask for advice
sincerely and you take advice and you
believe things with conviction you make
a statement in the environment the
environment moves around you the
environment changes this is what the
reality distortion field is I will get
to Mars by 2023 and the world says
you're crazy it's impossible he's been
saying it for 20 years the guy's insane
clearly believe the same thing he's been
wrong for 20 years but in retrospect
he's always right and this is the same
same thing with Trump he's the biggest
idiot who always happens to be right but
I'll pause there there's a quality of
attunement that we've touched on too
right where you know it's interesting
it's like there's also something that
goes on below the level of speech and
cognition right which i think is
constantly going on in relationships
which is like come is also is for
came on when we learned how to speak
like since you today we don't like
babies don't acquire language through
understanding the word that they're
saying they do it through mimicry and I
think that there's there's a real deep
thing that goes on that when you're
paying attention to the other person
while you're speaking you can you're
registering subtle ways in which they're
paying attention not paying attention
and and your body kind of innately
can begin to could be present - they're
listening as you're speaking it's one of
the things that I noticed what would
happen to me and like even when I would
like I'd lead courses and then when we
were first we were first leading courses
it's like I had never done it before
right and and I would I
there was always parts before we would
start circling where I would set up the
conversation by like like having uh like
like doing the talk on a certain
distinction or a framework or something
right to set up set it up and then
sometimes it would just rock and then
other times it would just call fall flat
and I was real identified with it so I'd
feel really really bad would it fell
flat and I feel really good when it
didn't but like it was the same
conversation I would I would have the
same conversation and then one would
would really fly and the other one
wouldn't and I for the longest time I
couldn't tell what the difference was
until I started to realize like that oh
when it went well what was driving the
conversation were the relationships and
the people in the room and that when it
went badly like is was when I was trying
to when I would disconnect from the
people and I get self-conscious and I
was so focused on what I wanted to say
and so then I started to see that
distinction and I get in front of the
room and like what would happen is is
like when I saw myself kind of get like
just trying to focus on what I was
saying I would bring my attention back
to the people in the room and I would
just look at one person and start
speaking to them and
that then that just started to become
more and more the way that I I had
conversations in front of the room with
people where it just became second
nature to where because it's all
whenever we're speaking with there's
always a listening that's going on and
then just being attuned into the
listening and allowing what I say to be
in direct relationship to the listening
is I'll start to speak speak things that
are attuned into the room and are
completely irrelevant right I just want
to check in with you guy it's it's been
two hours now and well I don't want to
stop you if you if you want to keep
going but I want to be respectful of
your time as well oh yeah I I should I
should probably go it's been a couple
hours but this is been great this has
been fantastic it's been fascinating and
you know we'd certainly love to have you
back at any time
yeah and I want to draw people's
attention to the voices with for Vicky
that guy did recently with John and is a
couple other conversations on John's
channel plus a bunch of conversations on
guy's channel so you've had you've had a
quite a bit of a back-and-forth with
John there's some great discussions yeah
totally
yeah I'll give you I can put up a link
to my channel sure sure that would be
great and I can put it put one up too
this has been this has been amazing
we're so grateful for for your time I
think and the interaction is just the
the getting in deep and that's that's
fantastic really loved it I appreciate
it I appreciate the way that you held
the space like I could feel I could feel
your involvement and like you're leaning
in and thinking new things and being
interested in asking questions and that
really set a good tone for me thank you
well great thank you very much
appreciate it and think and thank you to
Tyler for recording as always and to
everybody here for for tuning in and
participating such a great community
that were
we're forming here and each conversation
seems to be getting getting better and
better
so it's it's really nice - nice to see
ya nice to meet everybody I hope I get a
chance to talk to all of you it may be
here at some point
thank you guy that was great thank you
guy and thanks to everyone who's here
thank you guys bye you're amazing thanks
again